Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adapted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Support our volunteers: magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: Unfortunate Love
I can cut a thousand strands of hair
but I cannot sever the tangled threads of my mind.
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Support our volunteers: magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
You two are like sisters to each other.
When she is having the meat to herself,
how can she forget to share a bowl of the broth?
Your Highness hopes the Analects for Women
will remind the harem of good manners.
I do understand that jealousy and spite
are the gravest flaws in a woman's virtue.
Though I am dull-witted,
I won't tolerate flaws in my character.
Although you have no moral failings,
you can't expect the other concubines to be the same.
Throughout all these years in the palace,
fickleness of the human heart has been a constant.
I thank Your Highness for the advice.
Copying down Analects for Women
will caution us against strife and rivalries.
Your Highness's thoughtfulness is profound.
We will follow your instructions.
It is very pleasant to converse with Lady Sourire.
And Lady Shen has learned from Lady Sourire
to better craft her words.
You two shouldn't be underestimated.
I'm tired from all the talking this morning.
We will go.
Now you know how it is.
I know how Consort Fleur is.
But Meizhuang, do you blame me?
If it weren't you, there would be someone else.
Instead of someone else, I'd rather it be you..
Between us, the other concubines
might harm me if they gain favor.
But Huan'er, you won't.
Meizhuang.
You are the only one I can trust
among so many in the palace.
We are friends with Lingrong
but it's not the same as growing up together.
How will we live through the decades to come
if we can't support each other?
Meizhuang, there have been events I couldn't
foresee and therefore prevent.
No matter what the future holds,
our sisterhood will never change.
Even though I have gained favor from His Majesty,
I hope you won't feel distanced from me.
With the qualities we possess,
it's no surprise His Majesty favors you and me.
Our favor isn't guaranteed to last,
but we must keep our lives to protect our families.
(thunder rumbling)
Why are you awake?
I heard the rain outside.
Do you have something on your mind?
No.
Don't lie to me.
Your Majesty, I'm scared.
I'm here. There's nothing to be afraid of.
Your Majesty treats me so well.
Has Your Majesty ever heard that
the most beloved concubine is also the most resented?
Did anyone give you trouble?
No, no one did.
The rain falls evenly on every flower in the harem
so they can bear fruits and carry on Heaven's blessings.
I dare not be exclusively favored by Your Majesty.
What if I insist so?
The harem is inextricably intertwined with the court.
"Plucking a single hair affects the whole body."
Your Majesty is a sagacious emperor.
Sagacious?
It's been seven days.
If the harem becomes plagued by strife, Your Majesty
won't be at peace while governing state affairs.
Neglecting the other concubines could bring complaints
about the fickleness of Your Majesty's heart.
I cannot let Your Majesty be troubled. I can't bear to.
All right.
Peace and grace to Imperial Mother.
Have a seat.
Thank you, Imperial Mother.
You seem to be in good spirits today.
Are you satisfied with the concubines serving you lately?
Among the new concubines,
I've taken a liking to Noble Lady Sourire.
Noble Lady Sourire?
I don't recall you mentioning her before.
She's the clever one who entered the palace last year.
She was ill for a long time, but has recovered recently.
That's good.
It's important that you have someone close to your heart.
Unlike Prince XVII. He still hasn't settled down with a wife.
He hasn't been visiting for some days.
I wonder how he has been.
Imperial Mother, if you miss him,
I'll summon him to come at noon.
He is a filial son.
But seeing him reminds me of his birth mother, Consort Serein.
Your father favored her exclusively, and she became the target of resentment and jealousy.
That always makes me feel unhappy.
An old woman likes to chatter
when she's idle and overthinking.
I benefit from your golden advice, Imperial Mother.
When you have time,
I'll send Lady Sourire here to seek your teaching.
There are more ladies in the harem than there are flowers.
Noble Ladies are like the ubiquitous little wildflowers.
I'll see her when she makes it to Concubine.
Certainly.
Madam Sun, Imperial Mother has been feeling unwell.
Has Consort Fleur visited her?
Her Highness has been busy assisting in the palace affairs.
The Empress came this morning to serve medicine.
But Concubine Beauté was here yesterday
and stayed for quite a long talk.
Concubine Beauté.
(noticing the name tag for Concubine Beauté)
The writing on Concubine Beauté's name tag is illegible.
Make a new one.
Her name tag won't be sent in for a few days.
(touching the name tag of Lady Sourire)
Peace to Consort Astuce.
Xiao-Xiazi, what brought you here?
Your Highness, His Majesty is on the way to your palace.
So I came here to notify Your Highness.
His Majesty is coming?
Is His Majesty really?
Yes.
Quickly, clean up here.
And over there.
- Ouch!
- Your Highness.
Your Highness, please be careful.
Such a shambles, how can I greet His Majesty?
Your Highness has served His Majesty all these years.
You know His Majesty inside and out.
His Majesty hasn't visited for almost a year.
Why is he coming all of a sudden?
Is Your Highness not happy?
I am. I am.
Go get a dress for me.
The pink one. His Majesty likes me in pink.
- Go quickly.
- Yes, Your Highness.
- Don't just stand there. Do my hair!
Wait, go send for the Third Prince.
Your Highness, His Majesty is coming to see you.
You should spend time talking to him.
How can you have an intimate conversation
if the Third Prince is here?
That's true. That child's speech is so coarse.
He might upset His Majesty again.
- Never mind, do my hair.
- Yes.
Allow me to take my leave.
Your Highness, please take a break and have some bird's nest.
Did His Majesty select her again?
His Majesty went to visit Consort Astuce.
Really? Her?
Anyone is good, as long as it's not Lady Sourire.
What hour is it now?
The night just began to fall.
His Majesty was hoping that Lady Shen
could learn about bookkeeping.
I will teach her carefully.
Go bring Lady Shen here.
Yes.
The candles are dazzling bright.
Put out a few for me.
Yes.
My Lady, don't wait up.
His Majesty has selected Consort Astuce's name tag
and went to the Palace of Eternal Spring.
That's just as well.
It sounds like you are happy but also upset, My Lady.
I'm confused as well.
I was hoping His Majesty would not come today,
but I feel unhappy when he doesn't.
I didn't expect an educated daughter of a respectable family
to write with such a poor hand.
The candlelight was dim and I couldn't see very well.
I hope Your Highness can forgive me.
You understand the colossal amounts of spending
from copying the account book.
As the head of the concubines,
I have to set an example of frugality.
I believe that the greatest scribes can
write beautifully even with their eyes closed.
The lighting is not a sufficient excuse.
I ... will make another copy for Your Highness.
Go ahead. I will have a doze.
Songzhi, the light is too bright.
Blow out two more candles.
Yes.
Have a seat.
I'm all right to stand by Your Majesty.
I'm not tired.
You're blocking the light. How can I read?
The light...
Your Majesty, chrysanthemum tea can help
relieve eye strain from reading at night.
You just brought me ginseng tea.
I forgot... Your Majesty.
Your Majesty, the Third Prince has grown taller.
He's already reached adulthood, and still growing?
Oh, I mean, he grew stronger.
He listened to Your Majesty,
and goes to the hunting ground every day.
The Third Prince follows Your Majesty's guidance strictly.
I hope he does remember what I said.
He does, he studies late every night,
and rises before dawn to practice horseback archery.
I say to him every time I see him:
"Hongshi, you must listen to your Father;
You must live up to his expectations as his eldest son;
I hope you can share some of your Father's burden in the future."
Listening to all those words must have worn out his ears,
and mine too.
Do you not have something else to say to your son?
Yes, I ...
The dress doesn't look good on you.
Don't wear it again.
Your Majesty, I remember you saying you like me in pink.
Pink is a delicate color.
It's not for your age.
Does Your Majesty think I'm old?
I'm just being honest.
Lake blue and emerald green are
much more appropriate for your status.
Don't stay up late.
Where is Your Majesty going?
Back to the Hall of Mental Cultivation.
Your Majesty ... Your Majesty ...
After so long, Consort Astuce must be
very happy to see His Majesty.
Don't overthink, My Lady.
You should rest early.
"Rain pours over Lake Dongting;
mist clouds over Temple Huangling."
"My eyes pine for my husband but see him not;
I cannot rise above the haze over the ruffled water."
My Lady, don't play this song.
It's bad luck to play "The Lament of the Xiang River Concubines."
The Lament of the Xiang River Concubines.
Concubines' love can't draw attention,
let alone their lament.
Why should I even lament? I asked him to go.
Stop.
Is Your Majesty going back or to the Palace of Earthly Honor?
To the Palace of Pearl Jade.
Stop.
Put down the sedan.
It's "The Lament of the Xiang River Concubines."
I don't know music, Your Majesty.
"I can distinctly hear the clouds of sorrow pouring rain;
As though the winds also lament a man who won't return."
[quoted from another poem
"Listening to The Lament of the Xiang River Concubines"]
She's sad when I'm not with her.
Your music disquiets my heart.
Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
Rise.
What brings Your Majesty here?
"Pale and haggard grows the yearner for his lover."
I learned what that feels like today.
Did Your Majesty not visit Consort Astuce?
I did pay her a visit.
I saw the beautiful moonlight on my way back,
and wondered what you were doing.
Fortunately, I didn't miss your wonderful zither playing.
If I accept Your Majesty's flattery,
there will be no place left for me to stand.
How can a lofty emperor take to eavesdropping?
How bold of you!
You'll play another song as punishment.
Consort Astuce must feel sad that Your Majesty left.
Would you not feel sad if I stayed with her?
I have agreed that Your Majesty is a sagacious emperor.
I will be sagacious tomorrow.
Tonight, I will be foolish once more.
Then I'll be a virtuous concubine tomorrow
and entreat Consort Astuce's forgiveness.
Si Lang, what do you want to hear?
["The fourth son", it's an endearment to call one's husband by birth order]
What did you just call me?
I misspoke, Your Majesty.
No, I like it when you call me that.
Your name is Zhen Huan.
What is the milk name your family calls you?
I don't have one.
Then can I call you Huan Huan?
Huan Huan.
(yawning)
You have finished?
Your Highness, I made two copies of each book
in compensation for my poor handwriting.
Please take a look, Your Highness.
The hour is late. You shall leave now.
I will let you know after I read through them.
Yes, I bid Your Highness goodbye.
Consort Fleur was clearly making things difficult for you.
The account book was full of numbers,
and she dimmed the lights down.
Your eyes were red after writing the two copies.
What can I do? She's Consort Fleur.
Why don't you tell His Majesty, My Lady?
She is teaching me in the name of His Majesty's behest.
Even if His Majesty helps me with this,
will he let me continue to learn about palace management?
I won't do it. I'd lose more than I gain.
I'm just worried about you, My Lady.
All right, I don't feel tired anymore.
The Thousand Carp Pond is in the vicinity.
Let's go for a walk.
His Majesty had more lamps lit up there
so we can see the red fish at night.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组🐡
Support our volunteers: magpiebridgebrigade.cn
We are running out of fish food.
Xiao-Shi, go fetch some more.
Yes.
Look at that, My Lady.
I've finally found you, My Lady.
I've been looking around.
What brings you out at night, Madam?
Is there anything I can do for Her Highness?
Her Highness was going to reward you
with the ink offered as tribute from Anhui Province.
But you were already out of sight.
Then, Lunar will go with you, Madam.
- But you'll be here alone, My Lady.
- You'll be back shortly.
Help! H... Help!
Help!
His Majesty the Emperor.
I bow in respect before Your Majesty.
Rise.
- I thank Your Majesty.
- How is Meizhuang?
My Lady, Noble Lady Shen is out of danger.
But she is still unconscious due to shock and inhaling water.
We have written prescriptions for her to
recover quickly from the aftereffects.
However ...
Don't mince your words.
Yes, I was going to say that it might take
quite some time for Lady Shen to make a full recovery,
especially to recuperate from the severe shock.
You've always been Lady Shen's doctor.
You must spare no effort in her care.
Yes.
We will go prepare the herbs.
No need for formalities.
Meizhuang.
Is this how you attend your mistress?
I beg Your Majesty's pardon.
Explain in detail. How did Lady Shen fall into the pond?
Your Highness, I do not know.
How careless!
You're her personal servants, how can you not know?
Your Highness, we really don't know.
I was going to get more fish food
while My Lady was feeding the carp.
The news came to me when I was on my way.
Lunar, what about you?
Songzhi told us that Consort Fleur
had some ink to reward to My Lady.
I went with her when she found us by the pond.
In that case, not a servant was with Lady Shen when she fell?
Your Majesty, Consort Fleur is here.
What brings you here so late at night?
I hurried here after hearing that Lady Shen nearly drowned.
Is Lady Shen better now?
Look for yourself.
Poor thing. A girl as pretty as a flower has to suffer like this.
Your Highness, please don't worry. The doctors said
she will be fine when she regains consciousness.
Your Majesty, the guards were lax in their patrol,
so they couldn't come to Lady Shen's timely rescue.
This is my negligence in managing the palace.
I shall receive Your Majesty's punishment.
The guards patrol on scheduled shifts.
If you are to be punished, the Empress should
also be held responsible as the head of the harem.
Stupid servants! How were you serving your mistress?
You're worrying His Majesty.
How incompetent.
These servants are only a burden to Lady Shen.
I suggest they be sent to the Department of Penalty.
Your Majesty, Xiao-Shi and Lunar didn't act appropriately.
But they do not deserve to be sent to the Department of Penalty.
This is to maintain discipline in the palace.
If there are more servants like them,
the imperial ponds will be our drowning pits.
Concubine Estime, you are also responsible for the
inept servants in your palace.
I will follow Your Highness's advice
and strictly discipline the servants.
I am guilty of not taking good care of My Lady.
I beg Your Highness to allow me to serve My Lady until she awakes
before I report myself to the Department of Penalty.
Shameless lackey!
Are you waiting for your mistress
to wake up and intercede for you?
I wish Your Highness would pardon her.
Lunar and Xiao-Shi didn't properly attend Meizhuang,
but they aren't to blame for the accident.
Instead of punishing them, why not allow them
to redeem themselves by looking after Meizhuang？
"A merit expiates a crime."
Lady Sourire, don't you think a crime deserves punishment?
Leniency towards these two servants
may send out the message to many
that servants can be exempt from punishment
if they compensate for their mistakes.
It's only right to separate punishment and compensation.
But Lunar and Xiao-Shi have served Meizhuang all along.
If Meizhuang's trusted servants were sent away at this juncture,
that wouldn't be good for her recovery.
Why should they stay with Lady Shen now
when they have failed to even look after her?
The Thousand Carp Pond is less than a hundred feet from my palace.
How can I tolerate such a mistake in my realm?
Your Highness, that is also what I'm concerned about.
Your Highness makes fair decisions about awards and punishments.
But others might think that Your Highness is so irate
because the incident happened near your palace
rather than because Your Highness cares about Lady Shen.
What matters is not punishing the servants
but protecting Your Highness's prestige.
I hope Your Highness will reconsider.
I agree with Lady Sourire.
Why don't we wait until Lady Shen awakes
and then decide on the punishments for her servants?
Your Majesty, I wonder if it's appropriate
for me to make another suggestion.
Go ahead.
We don't know how Meizhuang fell into the pond.
But she fell unconscious because of the guards' delay in their rescue.
I would suggest replacing the guards
at the Palace of Earthly Honor
in case they repeat their carelessness
and Her Highness suffers a similar accident.
Lady Sourire just said "a merit expiates a crime."
And now you want to replace my palace guards?
Is that a fair way to mete out punishment?
I'm thinking for Your Highness.
His Majesty esteems Your Highness.
How can such negligent guards
attend to Your Highness's palace?
That would cause hazards in your place of dwelling.
Besides, we are simply replacing guards.
It is not a punishment.
Nothing else matters as much as safety.
This must not happen again.
Su Peisheng will select elite guards for your palace tomorrow
so I can be at ease.
I thank Your Majesty for your concern.
I brought Lady Shen the best wild ginseng
to nourish her health from the aftereffects.
Not a moment have you stopped looking after the harem.
You are still exerting yourself so late at night.
You should go have some rest.
Your Majesty as well.
You rise for the court early every morning.
I had my servants cooking ejiao longan soup when I left.
It must be ready by now.
Would Your Majesty like to have some before you sleep?
You're always so thoughtful.
I do feel a little hungry.
Would you like to go with us?
The Palace of Earthly Honor makes the best food in the palace.
I am terribly flattered, Your Majesty.
Lady Sourire, you should come with us.
I am not blessed to deserve the finest food.
I hope Your Majesty will have one more serving in my stead.
I wish to stay here to look after Meizhuang.
All right, but mind your own health as well.
I bid Your Majesty goodbye.
I bid Your Highness goodbye.
His Majesty departs.
It's very late now.
Your Highness should return and rest.
Certainly, but don't exhaust yourself.
Is Your Highness not feeling tired yet?
Would you like something to eat?
I feel sorry for Lady Shen.
What does Your Highness make of this accident?
Ejiao longan soup.
Consort Fleur came well-prepared.
Both Your Highness and Lady Sourire stood alert.
Consort Fleur showed up here well dressed and coiffed.
She had planned every step of the way.
A fox must hide her tail well
when pretending to be a dog.
But she was so pleased with herself, she let her tail slip.
She wouldn't bother.
She was so determined, she had that soup brewing as an invitation.
Of course she couldn't dress any less nicely.
But His Majesty might have been
too worried about Lady Shen to see that.
Should we point this out to His Majesty?
What good would that do?
Consort Fleur has her eye on our palace,
afraid to miss a single fault.
Let's not go to her door and point out a fault to her.
It's past midnight, My Lady.
You should get some sleep.
I can't. I'm anxious.
Me too, My Lady.
I just can't fathom how My Lady
could have lost her footing.
Recall carefully, did you see anything strange at that time?
It's just a suspicion I have, but
how could this happen the moment both of you left?
Now that Meizhuang is unconscious,
we'll all be kept in the dark if you forgot to mention anything.
My Lady, I know this is serious,
but I wasn't sure about what I saw and dared not say anything.
It is a serious matter.
That's why you must report every detail.
On my way back to the pond,
I might have seen a eunuch dashing past the pond.
But I couldn't see clearly in the dark.
Did you mention that to anyone else?
I didn't dare to bring it up with anyone.
Remember,
don't speak of this to anyone.
Do you understand?
Yes.
One word from that wretch
and His Majesty decided to replace my guards.
It's causing me so much inconvenience today.
Don't be upset, Your Highness.
It's not worth it.
How dare she tread on my face?
Your Highness need not worry.
Now that she is in favor,
she has enemies in every corner.
Who's serving Yu at the moment?
I heard her temper is so bad
that she even kicked out her maids.
Now she's all by herself.
That Kang Luhai in your palace is useless.
How about his apprentice? Is he loyal to you?
Did Your Highness mean Xiao-Yinzi?
He is all right, not as sly as his shifu.
Send him to serve Yu.
This is a gift from the Governor of Shandong Province.
[where Shen Meizhuang's father works]
I know nothing about ink sticks.
I hope Your Majesty will enlighten me.
This is the "Paired Mandarin Duck Ink."
It is hard as jade and smooth as lacquer.
It is decorated on both sides
with mandarin ducks in gold colors.
It's the finest of Shangdong Ink.
I know nothing else, but mandarin ducks are lifelong couples.
It's a symbol of harmony between you and His Majesty.
He's very good at playing to my liking.
[implication: the emperor received the ink from Shen's father's governor and gave it to the empress]
But the inkstick would be more useful
at the Palace of Earthly Honor.
The inkstick there was used to "lure the tiger into a snare."
It had a useful purpose but an evil one.
Don't speak your mind out loud.
Is Your Majesty not going to do anything
about Lady Shen's incident?
If you remember how Consort Fleur
strutted into my palace this morning,
you could tell that His Majesty has made a conclusion.
My strength is not enough to administer my will.
But we all know who is behind this.
It doesn't matter what we know
as long as His Majesty is not in the know.
His Majesty always wishes for a peaceful harem.
Some cases are settled by being unsettled.
Send Lady Shen some nourishing herbs
from the Imperial Dispensary.
Meizhuang, you're awake.
Are you feeling hungry?
Would you like something to eat?
Huan'er!
Someone ... was trying to kill me!
Meizhuang, did you see who it was?
He ... he pushed me from behind ...
I couldn't see his face.
He did it forcibly ...
It must be a eunuch or a guard!
There are countless eunuchs and guards in the palace.
Did you see who it was?
Anyone can be friendly on their face but not in their heart,
but no one would be so vicious as to take my life.
The only one who could possibly do this to me ... must be ...
But the Thousand Carp Pond is just
steps away from her Palace of Earthly Honor.
She chose to do it right where she lives...
Does she not even know to avoid drawing suspicions?
Suspicions?
That was the last thing she wanted to avoid.
She came here late at night,
dolled up and domineering,
and almost gave sentences to Lunar and Xiao-Shi.
She left triumphantly with His Majesty to her palace.
You were only a hundred steps away
and almost drowned outside her palace.
Whoever in the palace dares to
commit such a crime in her territory?
No one, other than herself.
"The battle is won by the most daring maneuvers."
No one would suspect that
she would do such a thing as set fire to herself.
Now that His Majesty favors you, she's wary that
our fledging wings might escape her control over the harem.
She tries to shoot one down
so the other will become a lone bird,
unable to contend against her.
Meizhuang, I'm so sorry.
I got you into this nightmare.
It has nothing to do with you.
She had already seen me as fishbone in her throat
when I gained favor.
She didn't do anything early on
due to His Majesty's attention to me and my utmost forbearance.
Meizhuang, what do you plan to do now?
What can I do?
I have no evidence against
His Majesty's beloved consort.
I will tell His Majesty
that I ...
that I lost my footing.
That might be all we can do for now.
I'm unable to do anything this time,
but I won't let her have her way all my life.
As long as I'm breathing,
I'm counting every second!
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Support our volunteers: magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: The Phoenix Taking Flight
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
The dreams I dimly recall;
The past I hardly remember,
amidst the autumn moons and the spring flowers.
Like the moon's reflection on water
or flowers seen through mist - floating and drifting.
The joyous sounds you brought;
The silence you left;
Changing faster than clouds can turn to rain.
Our minds resonated;
Our hearts beat in unison;
But we lost what we once possessed.
A poem to converse;
A melody to accompany;
A heart to bind to mine.
I hoped for endless longing and eternal promise,
but I’m left with only the flute and the zither.
With affection, I pleased;
With my heart, I committed;
With my arms, I embraced.
I desired to be remembered;
Desired to be cherished;
Why am I only hated and deceived?
My wish ran against my will.
Behold the mockery of destiny and the game of fate.
My unwavering love is gone
like flowers swept away in the wind.
Praying for a bright moon;
Praying for a rising sun;
Dreaming to bask in the spring breezes.
But the unsparing northern winds carry snow and rain
to destroy the aspirations of the plum tree.
A phoenix about to take flight rustles its wings
but the arc of its flight is unseen.
The phoenix tree sways in the wind,
shedding memories in the whispers of the falling leaves.